{"tossups": [{"question": "A man who claimed allegiance to this colony despite living in one to its north prompted mob violence that became known as Cresap\u2019s War. The leader of this colony petitioned Queen Anne after another colony was granted land below the 40th parallel. After Richard Ingle and William Claiborne took control of this colony, Jesuit priests were sent back to England during the \"Plundering Time.\" For ten points, name this colony, whose first Proprietary-Governor was Leonard Calvert.", "answer": "<b><u>Maryland</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Calutron was made as part of this project for use with the Y-12 Project. Personnel of this project worked throughout Europe in Operation Alsos. For this project, Kenneth Nichols negotiated with the Eldorado Gold Mines and the Union Miniere [[meen-YEHR]] du Haut-Katanga which ran the Shinkolobwe [[sheen-koh-LOH-bweh]] Mine in Belgian Congo. This project created the Thin Man gun-type design. Leslie Groves and Robert Oppenheimer directed this project, which had sites in Oak Ridge and Los Alamos. For ten points, name this project which produced the first atomic bomb.", "answer": "<b><u>Manhattan</u></b> Project (accept <b><u>Development of Substitute Materials</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While mayor, this politician implemented the Care Not Cash initiative to expand housing options. This politician led the Parking and Traffic Commission under Willie Brown. This man came under fire for hosting a birthday party at the French Laundry restaurant amid COVID-19. This man oversaw the cessation of executions at San Quentin Prison and appointed the first inspector general of his state\u2019s BART transit system. For ten points, name this man who was elected governor of California in 2018.", "answer": "Gavin <b><u>Newsom</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Under this king, Peter de la Mare was chosen as speaker. Both the Good and Bad Parliaments operated under this king, whom William of Wykeham [[WIK-um]] helped develop Windsor Castle. The \"Lady of the Sun,\" Alice Perrers [[peh-REHR]], had an affair with this ruler. This ruler rose to power after removing Roger Mortimer and formed the Order of the Garter in 1348. This king, whose son was the Black Prince, won at Cr\u00e9cy and Poitiers [[pwah-TYEH]] against France. For ten points, name this English king who began the Hundred Years' War.", "answer": "<b><u>Edward III</u></b> (accept <b><u>Edward of Windsor</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. Frank \u201cBig Black\u201d Smith was tortured during one of these events, which was led in part by Weather Underground member Sam Melville. That example of these events was sparked by the killing of George Jackson. Participants in one of these events took control of the \"D Yard,\" which led Nelson Rockefeller to call in the National Guard. For ten points, name this type of event which occurred in September 1971 at Attica Correctional Facility, involving an uprising of over 2,200 inmates.", "answer": "<b><u>Prison Riot</u></b> (accept synonyms for <b><u>Prison</u></b> such as <b><u>Penitentiary</u></b> or <b><u>Jail</u></b>; accept synonyms for <b><u>riot</u></b> such as <b><u>uprising</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While working for this institution, Frank Hartman invented the liquid oxygen tent. This place was the first of its kind to implement the closed staff system. A painting set in this place contains a snail as well as a red ribbon representing an umbilical cord and was created by Frida Kahlo following a miscarriage. A home near this location named for its founder's wife, Clara, housed nursing students. For ten points, name this Detroit medical institution named for an automobile business magnate.", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Ford Hospital</u></b> (accept <b><u>HFH</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Since its rediscovery in 1849, the exploits of the eponymous hero of this poem and his hairy friend, Enkidu, across ancient Iraq have been referenced in many forms of media from Philip Roth\u2019s <em>The Great American Novel</em> to the video game <em>Civilization</em>. The hero of this poem visits Utnapishtim, who recounts a story of how he survived a global flood by building a giant boat from reeds. Found in Nineveh by Austen Henry Layard, this poem was originally written on twelve cuneiform tablets. For ten points, what is the name of this Sumerian epic poem?", "answer": "The Epic of <b><u>Gilgamesh</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "In this country, a march on Sonsonate [[sohn-soh-NAH-teh]] was organized by Feliciano Ama. A neighbor targeted this country\u2019s Ilopango airbase during a war named for its hundred hour length. An activist in this country named Farabundo Mart\u00ed lends his name to its FMLN party. In this country, Roberto D'Aubuisson [[doh-bwee-SOHN]], who founded the ARENA party, may have ordered the killing of Bishop \u00d3scar Romero. The Football War was fought between this country and its northeastern neighbor, Honduras. For ten points, name this Central American country which fought a thirteen-year Civil War.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>El Salvador</u></b> (accept Rep\u00fablica de <b><u>El Salvador</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A line of defense named for this man stretched from the Baltic Sea to the Carpathians. Maxim Litvinov was replaced by this man, who was ordered to purge a ministry of Jews. Georgy Malenkov and this man teamed up against Nikita Khrushchev in the failed Anti-Party Group takeover. This man secretly planned to partition Poland in a pact he signed with Joachim von Ribbentrop. The foreign minister for Joseph Stalin, for ten points, who was this man who names a type of improvised explosive known as his \"cocktail\"?", "answer": "Vyacheslav <b><u>Molotov</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "While working for this publication, Janet Cooke won a Pulitzer Prize for her story about an eight-year-old heroin addict named Jimmy, though it was later revealed that the story was largely a fabrication. Under the editorship of Ben Bradlee, this publication published a series of documents detailing U.S. involvement in Southeast Asia. Jeff Bezos purchased this newspaper in 2013 for $250 million. For ten points, name this newspaper which published the Pentagon Papers after the <em>New York Times</em> was barred from doing so.", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Washington Post</u></b></em> (accept <b><u>WaPo</u></b>; prompt on \u201cThe Post\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An 1870 disaster affecting this company may have inspired a P.G. Wodehouse novel sold in the U.S. as <em>Three Men and a Maid</em>. A trio of particularly large entities designed for this company was created by Harland and Wolff. Edward Smith was employed by this company, which was bought out by their rival, Cunard. Based in Liverpool, this company's best known asset was discovered by the archaeologist Robert Ballard many decades after it met its demise in 1912. For ten points, name this ocean liner company which owned the <em>Titanic</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>White Star</u></b> Line (or <b><u>Oceanic Steam Navigation</u></b> Company)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Ash Upson ghostwrote a story about this man's best known action. Carl Adamson\u2019s refusal to purchase an additional 600 goats that were allegedly left out of a count prevented this man from breaking a lease and set off a series of events resulting in his death, perhaps at the hands of Jesse Brazel. After losing a state senate race, this man joined the Texas Rangers and earlier served as Lincoln County sheriff, in which capacity he visited an acquaintance of Pete Maxwell who asked \u201cWho is It?\u201d For ten points, name this lawman who shot Billy the Kid.", "answer": "Pat <b><u>Garrett</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Hackers targeted this state-owned company in 2012 with the Shamoon virus, possibly in retaliation for the U.S.'s involvement in Stuxnet. A 2019 drone attack conducted by Houthi rebels targeted two of this company's plants, disrupting global crude output by five percent. Months later, this company held an IPO on the Tadawul stock exchange with an estimated market cap of $1.88 trillion. For ten points, name this state-owned oil company of a certain Middle Eastern kingdom.", "answer": "Saudi <b><u>Aramco</u></b> (accept <b><u>Saudi Arabian</u></b> Oil Company; prompt on \"Arabian-American Oil Company\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This mountain range's Rockfish Gap was the site of a Mountain Top Tavern meeting attended by John Marshall and Thomas Jefferson at which they discussed founding a university. A railroad named for this mountain range aimed to connect Piedmont with the Shenandoah Valley. Following the Indian Removal Act, many Cherokee hid on lands in this mountain range, which became Great Smoky Mountains National Park. Part of the Appalachians, for ten points, what is this colorfully named range?", "answer": "<b><u>Blue Ridge</u></b> Mountains (prompt on \"Appalachians\")", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This author likely drew inspiration from the surgeon Joseph Bell for one of his characters, who tracks down ex-KKK members in the story \u201cFive Orange Pips.\" Jefferson Hope offers two pills, one of which is poisoned, to two enemies in a novel by this author, the first of four full-length novels to feature this author's best known character. A cab driver is tracked down by the Baker Street Irregulars in a book by, for ten points, what author, whose novel <em>A Study in Scarlet</em> features the detective Sherlock Holmes?", "answer": "Arthur Conan <b><u>Doyle</u> </b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This is the official nickname of one location, former nicknames of which referenced its vast amounts of hog and hominy and a river known by Native Americans as \u201cBig Bend.\u201d An event that inspired this nickname was partially fueled by the death of Davy Crockett. That event which may have inspired this nickname involved 30,000 individuals responding to James K. Polk\u2019s call for 2,600 troops during the Mexican-American War. For ten points, give this state nickname indicating the non-mandatory provision of armed forces from cities like Nashville.", "answer": "The <b><u>Volunteer</u></b> State (prompt on \"Tennessee\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this period, Louis Marie Turreau [[too-ROH]] used the \u201cInfernal Columns'' tactic in the War in the Vend\u00e9e [[vahn-DEH]]. At the height of this period, Jean-Baptiste Carrier [[kah-ree-YEH]] facilitated the death of former magistrates and members of the Catholic church in the Drowning at Nantes [[NAHNT]]. This period was ended by the Thermidorian Reaction, which included the ousting of the Committee of Public Safety. For ten points, name this tumultuous period of the French Revolution, known for mass executions of political opponents by guillotine.", "answer": "<b><u>Reign of Terror</u></b> (accept La <b><u>Grande Terreur</u></b> prompt on \u201cThe French Revolution\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>An insurrection in this town was started by Tom\u00e1s Romero and Pablo</u></b> <b><u>Montoya, who scalped Governor Charles Bent in front of his family. That revolt in this</u></b> <b><u>town involved the siege of Simeon Turley's mill and distillery in Arroyo Hondo as well</u></b> <b><u>as the Battles of Mora. The ashes of author (+)</u> D.H. Lawrence were interred on a ranch in this town, near where he stayed with wealthy patron Mabel Dodge Luhan. Ansel Adams and (*) </b>Georgia O'Keeffe were associated with an art colony in this town, which takes its name from an almost millennium-old pueblo. For ten points, name this New Mexico town.", "answer": "<b><u>Taos</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Historian William Dalrymple has called this man an \u201cunstable sociopath,\" and</u></b> <b><u>in 2020, petitions were signed calling for the removal of a statue of this man on</u></b> <b><u>London's King Charles Street. This man took the city of Arcot [[AR-kot]] in 1751</u></b> <b><u>during the Second (+)</u> Carnatic War to relieve an attack by Joseph-Francois Dupleix [[doo-PLEH]]. This man's policies have been identified as leading to the outbreak of a severe famine in (*) </b>Bengal in 1770. For ten points, name this man, who led the forces of the British East India Company to victory at the Battle of Plassey.", "answer": "Robert <b><u>Clive</u></b> (or 1st Baron <b><u>Clive</u></b>; accept <b><u>Clive</u></b> of India)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A magistrate from this historical region named John Hunyadi successfully led</u></b> <b><u>the resistance against the Ottomans in the 15th century \u201cLong Campaign.\u201d Michael the</u></b> <b><u>Brave, the imperial governor of this region, temporarily united this region with the</u></b> <b><u>neighboring (+)</u> Moldavia and Wallachia [[wuh-LAY-kee-uh]]. The Second Vienna Award gave the Kingdom of Hungary the northern reaches of this (*) </b>Romanian region. For ten points, name this region which means \u201cacross the woods\u201d in Latin.", "answer": "<b><u>Transylvania</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>When once asked if he held a patent, this man replied, \u201cCould you patent the</u></b> <b><u>sun?\u201d This man\u2019s postgraduate work under Thomas Francis paved the way for his</u></b> <b><u>best known discovery. Julius Youngner was among the members of this man\u2019s</u></b> <b><u>research lab at the University of (+)</u> Pittsburgh. This scientist was tasked with finding new variants of the three known strains of a virus for which he developed a countermeasure improved upon by (*) </b>Albert Sabin. For ten points, name this American developer of the polio vaccine.", "answer": "Jonas <b><u>Salk</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This author used the example of her first encounter with Sapphire from \"Amos</u></b> <b><u>n\u2019 Andy\" to claim that a certain image \"was not the body of desire.\u201d This author</u></b> <b><u>refuted Laura Mulvey in a work of film theory which criticized Michel Foucault [[foo-</u><u>KOH]] and coined the term (+)</u> \u201coppositional gaze.\u201d This critic of Daniel Patrick Moynihan claimed that the Black nationalist movement relied on misogyny to further its aims in a work named after a (*) </b>speech given in Ohio by Sojourner Truth. For ten points, name this feminist author of <em>Ain\u2019t I a Woman</em>.", "answer": "bell <b><u>hooks</u></b> (accept Gloria Jean <b><u>Watkins</u></b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Temirgoy are among the twelve main tribes of these people, who were</u></b> <b><u>unified by Inal the Radiant. Grigory Zass called for the use of these people in scientific</u></b> <b><u>experiments and helped carry out a campaign against them which is remembered on</u></b> <b><u>a day of mourning in (+)</u> Abkhazia. Cossack troops oversaw the forced deportation of this predominantly Muslim group from a region east of the (*) </b>Black Sea. For ten points, name this Caucasian ethnic group which was subjected to a nineteenth-century ethnic cleansing.", "answer": "<b><u>Circassian</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Adyghe</u></b>; accept <b><u>Adige</u></b> accept <b><u>\u00c7erkesler</u></b>; accept <b><u>\u010cerkesy</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This woman finished fourth in the 1977 Democratic mayoral primary in New</u></b> <b><u>York. That election was won by Ed Koch, with whom this woman co-sponsored the</u></b> <b><u>first federal gay rights bill, the Equality Act of 1974. This eco-feminist ran on the</u></b> <b><u>campaign slogan \"This (+)</u> woman's place is in the House\u2014the House of Representatives.\" This woman presided over the 1977 National Women's Conference and led Jimmy Carter's (*) </b>National Advisory Commission for Women. For ten points, name this Representative for New York\u2019s 20th district, nicknamed \"Battling Bella.\"", "answer": "Bella <b><u>Abzug</u></b> (accept <b><u>Battling Bella</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Manuel Yan was one of the survivors of a part of this event called the</u></b> <b><u>Pantingan River Massacre. Victims of this event were assembled in Mariveles and</u></b> <b><u>Bagac before being forced to their destination at Camp O'Donnell. The leader of this</u></b> <b><u>event, (+)</u> Masaharu Homma, was executed in the Tokyo Trials. This event was followed a month later by the Battle of (*) </b>Corregidor in Manila Bay. For ten points, name this event in which American and Filipino prisoners of war were forced to undergo a brutal \"march.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Bataan</u></b> Death March", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This battle was the subject of a \"counter-counterfactual\" essay by Winston</u></b> <b><u>Churchill, explaining World War One was avoided because of it. Fierce fighting took</u></b> <b><u>place during this battle at areas such as Devil's (+)</u> Den and the Peach Orchard. The Siege of Vicksburg ended a day after this battle, in which one side suffered major losses due to the failure of (*) </b>Pickett's Charge. For ten points, name this 1863 battle of the American Civil War, often called the \"turning point for the Union.\"", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Gettysburg</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}